A Guide to the W. Kenneth Riland papers FA1255
Rockefeller Archive Center
W. Kenneth Riland papers
1942-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Riland, W. Kenneth
FA1255
11.77 Cubic Feet (32 containers)
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material containing personal information on the W. Kenneth Riland family is closed until June 27, 2042.
Arrangement
The W. Kenneth Riland papers are arranged as follows:
Series 1: Diaries
Series 2: United States v Riland Tax Evasion Trial
Series 3: Personal
Series 4: Medical and Medical School Documents
Series 5: White House Papers from Nixon's Term
Series 6: Trips
Series 7: Nelson A. Rockefeller
Series 8: Clippings
Series 9: Scrapbook and Photographs
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The W. Kenneth Riland papers were donated by the Riland Family on June 27, 1992.
Biographical / Historical
W. Kenneth Riland was a leading figure in the field of osteopathic medicine and co-founder of the New York College of Osteopathic Medicine in Old Westbury, New York. He served as personal physician to Nelson A. Rockefeller and Richard M. Nixon, among other prominent figures. He accompanied Nelson Rockefeller on a number of trips including the 1969 trip to Latin America. He was also an associate of Richard Nixon and accompanied him on his trip to China.
Scope and Contents
The W. Kenneth Riland papers contain diaries, correspondence, campaign material, trial documents regarding Riland's tax evasion case, photographs, a scrapbook and assorted ephemera from various trips and events.
Osteopathic medicine; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979 -- Political and social views; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979); Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous) (1913-1994)
- Diaries, 1959-1987; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Riland kept a detailed diary from 1968-1972 and for intermittent periods between 1959-1968 and 1972-1979. Included in his diaries are trips with Nelson Rockefeller during Nelson's gubernatorial and presidential campaigns, as well as trips abroad before and during his vice presidency. Riland also kept detailed accounts of his trips with President Richard Nixon to Europe, Russian, the Middle East, and China. Riland also wrote about the business and personal sides of his life. Included in the diaries are recollections of conversations with Nelson, Happy, Laurance, and other members of the Rockefeller family, as well as discussions with Henry Kissinger, Chief Justice Burgher, Rose Mary Woods, John Mitchell, and many others Riland shared a social relationship with.
  Although Riland aimed to document events as they were despite having personal relationships and a sense of confidence with those he was documenting, it is important to note that these "diaries" were written with the intent that they would eventually be published.
  Riland originally used tapes to record his daily events, however the Archive Center does not have possession of these recordings. Riland's secretary transcribed the tapes to their current form. Most of the documents in this series are typed unless otherwise stated (e.g. there are some entries that are handwritten by Riland, but most of these also exist in typed form.) There are also duplicates of certain periods as well as folders that have overlapping dates that cover roughly the same period of time, plus or minus a few weeks.
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1968-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Special Trips with Richard M. Nixon and Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1959-1969 August 3; 1
    - West Coast Trip - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1959 November 11-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - West Coast Trip - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Edited Transcript, 1959 November 11-15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mid-West Trip - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1959 December 12-29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mid-West Trip - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Edited Transcript, 1959 December 12-29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mid-West Trip - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Itinerary and Ephemera, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - European Trip - Richard M. Nixon, 1969 February 22-March 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - European Trip - Richard M. Nixon - Handwritten, 1969 February 22-March 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - South American Mission - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1969 May 11-July 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - South American Mission - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Handwritten, 1969 May 11-30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Round the World with Richard M. Nixon, 1969 July 22-August 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Round the World with Richard M. Nixon - Handwritten, 1969 July 22-August 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Handwritten Diary, 1968 February 27-September 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Diary, 1968 February 27-September 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Diary and 1968 Campaign, 1968 February 27-May 12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Contains introductory information written by Riland about the scope of his diaries and his wishes for their publication and organization.
  - "The Nixon Saga", 1969 February 16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Recorded February 16, 1969. A transcription of a discussion between Riland and Austin Marshall covering the events leading up to the first visit to the White House and Nixon's European trip.
  - Diary, 1970 January 21-May 15 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Diary, 1970 June 27-September 8 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Diary, 1970 September 8-November 29 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Diary, 1970 November 29-1971 June 7 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tax Case Chronology, 1971 May 21-1973 April 10 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    General chronology, not detailed.
  - Handwritten Diary, 1971 January 7-March 25 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Diary, 1971 June 8-November 26 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Diary, 1971 November 26-1972 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Handwritten Diary, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - China Trip, 1972 February 17-March 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Review of China Trip, 1972 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Moscow Mission with President Nixon, 1972 May 19-June 11 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Russia Trip, 1972 May 21-June 12 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Israel Trip with Nelson A. Rockefeller - Handwritten, 1972 July 12-August 13 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Diary, 1972 July 12-December 31 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Diary, 1972 December 10-1973 February 21 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Diary, 1972 December 10-1973 July 21 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Handwritten Diary, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Diary, 1973 January 1-April 9 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Paris Trip, 1973 January 8-13 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Diary, 1973 February 21-March 6 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Diary, 1973 March 7-July 21 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Diary, 1973 April 9-September 17 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Diary, 1973 June 28-July 11 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Diary, 1973 July 12-December 31 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Telephone Conversation between Walter Tkach and Kenneth Riland, 1973 July 26 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Transcribed conversation about Riland's tax evasion case with associated notes/inferences from Riland.
  - Diary, 1973 September 18-December 31 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Diary, 1973 September 25-October 20 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Diary, 1974 January 1-February 20 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Diary, 1974 January 24-December 31 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
    March 3-July 15, 1974 missing - there are no entries during the time of the tax evasion trial.
  - Diary, 1975 January (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Diary, 1975 February (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Diary, 1975 March (Box 6, Folder 52)
    Last page includes a letter regarding the tax evasion pre-trial and trial.
  - Diary, 1975 April (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Diary, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Diary, 1975 June (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Diary, 1975 July (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Diary, 1975 August (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Diary, 1975 September (Box 6, Folder 58)
    Contains information on Nelson Rockefeller's trip to Texas, Oklahoma, and Arkansas.
  - Diary, 1975 October (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Diary, 1975 November (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Diary, 1975 December (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Diary, 1976 January (Box 6, Folder 62)
    Includes review of Spiro Agnew election, pardon of Jimmy Hoffa, and Riland's thoughts on the identity of "Deep Throat"
  - Diary, 1976 February (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Diary, 1976 March 3-April 3 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    Includes entries pertaining to the "Round the World Trip" with Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Handwritten Diary, 1976 March (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Diary, 1976 April 5-May 31 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Diary, 1976 June-September 25 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Handwritten Diary, 1976 September 25-October 27 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Contains ephemera and post cards.
  - Copies of Bound Diaries, 1959-1971; 2
    - "Special Trips" Binder - West Coast Trip, 1959 (Box 29, Folder 231)
    - "Special Trips" Binder - Mid-West Trip, 1959 (Box 29, Folder 232)
    - "Special Trips" Binder - European Trip with Richard M. Nixon, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 233)
    - "Special Trips" Binder - South American Mission, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 234)
    - "Special Trips" Binder - Round the World with Richard M. Nixon, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 235)
    - 1968 Campaign Diary - Tape 1 (Box 29, Folder 236)
    - 1968 Campaign Diary - Tape 2 (Box 29, Folder 237)
    - 1968 Campaign Diary - Tape 3 (Box 29, Folder 238)
    - Tape 8, 1971 June-November (Box 29, Folder 239)
    - Tape 9, 1971 June-December (Box 29, Folder 240)
    - Tape 10, 1971 June-December (Box 29, Folder 241)
    - Nixon Saga - Tape 1, undated (Box 29, Folder 242)
    - Nixon Saga - Tape 2, undated (Box 29, Folder 243)
    - Nixon Saga Binder - Tape A-1, undated (Box 29, Folder 244)
    - Nixon Saga Binder - Tape A-2, undated (Box 29, Folder 245)
    - Nixon Saga Binder - Tape 3, undated (Box 29, Folder 246)
    - Nixon Saga Binder - Tape 4, undated (Box 29, Folder 247)
    - Nixon Saga Binder - Miscellaneous Packet, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 248)
- United States v. Riland Tax Evasion Trial, 1973-1974; 2
  In 1974, Riland faced tax evasion charges in a widely publicized case in New York City. The case lasted several weeks from March-May 1974. Ultimately, the jury found Riland not guilty of the charges. This series contains news clippings, personal notes, and legal documents that were kept by Riland. A large portion of this series consists of the trial's transcripts as well as copies of the hearings before the trial, including the testimony and suppression hearings.
  - Suppression Hearings, 1973 January 2-February 22 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Pretrial Transcripts, 1973 May 3-1974 January 8 (Box 8, Folder 70-71)
  - Pretrial Conferences, 1973 May 3-1974 February 28 (Box 8, Folder 72-75, Box 9, Folder 76-77)
  - U.S. Senate Report of Proceedings, Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities - Senate Resolution 60: General Investigation, 1973 July 16-17 (Box 9, Folder 80-81)
  - Transcripts - Volume 1 (pages 1-716A), 1974 March 5-11 (Box 10, Folder 82-86)
  - Transcripts - Volume 2 (pages 718-1434), 1974 March 12-15 (Box 11, Folder 87-90)
  - Transcripts - Volume 3 (pages 1435-2021), 1974 March 18-21 (Box 12, Folder 91-94)
  - Transcripts - Volume 4 (pages 2023-2756), 1974 March 22-29 (Box 13, Folder 95-101)
  - Transcripts - Volume 5 (pages 2757-3483), 1974 March 29-April 16 (Box 14, Folder 102-111)
  - Transcripts - Volume 6 - Weiner Cross-Examination Continued (pages 2829-2965), 1974 April 2 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Transcripts - Volume 7 (pages 4181-4778), 1974 April 16-29 (Box 15, Folder 113-121)
  - Transcripts - Volume 8 (pages 4779-5416), 1974 April 26-May 3 (Box 16, Folder 122-127)
  - Transcripts - Volume 9 (pages 5418-5748A), 1974 May 6-8 (Box 17, Folder 128-130)
  - Transcripts - Volume 9 [additional copies of May 8th transcript] (pages 5576-5748A), 1974 May 8 (Box 17, Folder 131-132)
  - Transcripts - Volume 9 [additional copies] (pages 5592-5679, 5681-5741, 5592) (Box 17, Folder 133-136)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 27, Folder 216)
  - Correspondence - Defense Fund Thank You Letters, 1974 (Box 27, Folder 217)
  - Correspondence - Sympathy Notes, 1974 (Box 27, Folder 218)
  - Boris Kostelanetz, 1974-1979 (Box 27, Folder 219)
  - Electronic Surveillance Documentation, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 220)
  - Wiretap Affidavit, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 221)
  - Copies of Court Papers, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 222)
  - Nixon and the IRS, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 223)
  - Trial Documents, 1973-1982 (Box 28, Folder 224-226)
  - Tax Questions, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 227)
  - Clippings and Notes, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 228-229)
  - "Rose Mary's Boo-Boo" Newsweek [Rose Mary Woods, Nixon's Private Secretary], 1973 December 10 (Box 28, Folder 230)
- Personal, 1942-1989; 3
  This series contains obituaries, news clippings, appointment calendars, a biographical sketch, family history papers, personal memos, invitations, and artifacts of Riland's time in Albany and Washington.
  - Biographical Sketch, 1975-1978 (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - Riland Family History, 1942-1973 (Box 18, Folder 138)
  - Appointment Calendars, 1969, 1970, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 139-140)
  - Washington Square Village Apartment, 1964-1976 (Box 18, Folder 141)
  - Rockefeller Plaza Automobile Accident, 1958 April (Box 18, Folder 142)
  - Obituary and IRS Clippings, 1973-1989 (Box 18, Folder 143)
  - Invitations and Mementos, 1968-1979 (Box 18, Folder 144)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 19, Folder 145)
    Memorabilia related to Mexico and New Zealand trips, Dr. Riland's Physician to the Governor Badge, notepads, and contact cards.
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Notes, 1947-1978 (Box 19, Folder 146)
  - Miscellaneous Notepad, undated (Box 30, Folder 252)
- Medical and Medical School Documents, 1958-1983; 4
  This series contains information on the New York State School of Osteopathy which was founded by Riland, as well as the Post Graduate Institute of Osteopathy. Also included are documents pertaining to foreign medicine, and acupuncture.
  - New York College of Osteopathic Medicine, 1976-1978 (Box 19, Folder 147)
  - Postgraduate Institute of Osteopathic Medicine and Surgery, 1967-1970 (Box 19, Folder 148)
  - Letters of Recommendation to Osteopathic Colleges, 1969-1970 (Box 19, Folder 149)
  - Russian Diagnostic Kit, 1972-1973 (Box 19, Folder 150)
    Includes an introductory manual for the acupuncture instrument called the "Tobiscope-2" in both English and Russian.
  - Chinese Medicine, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 151)
    - Anatomy poster (Folder 1)
  - Mayo Clinic Diet, undated (Box 19, Folder 152)
  - Subscriptions to Medical Journals, 1964-1983 (Box 19, Folder 153)
  - Relationship of SCUBA Diving to the Development of Aviator's Decompression Sickness, 1969-1973 (Box 19, Folder 154)
  - Theron G. Randolph (Allergist), 1967-1976 (Box 19, Folder 155)
  - Dr. Hugh Leavell's Report on Osteopathic Medicine, 1958-1961 (Box 19, Folder 156)
  - Letter to Merle C. Bundy, Medical Director, United States Steel Corporation, 1974 May 15 (Box 19, Folder 157)
    Riland talks about the affects of his indictment and trial.
  - Miscellaneous Medical Documents, 1969-1983 (Box 30, Folder 253)
- White House Papers from Nixon's Term, 1942-1976; 5
  This series contains memos, congressional and senate papers, campaign schedules, as well as the commutation papers of Jimmy Hoffa, and magazine covers autographed by Nixon and Haldeman.
  - White House Correspondence, 1969-1976 (Box 20, Folder 158)
  - White House Invitations and Memorabilia, 1969-1973 (Box 20, Folder 159)
  - Henry A. Kissinger, 1972-1973 (Box 20, Folder 160)
  - Commutation of Jimmy Hoffa, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 161)
  - Autographed Magazine Covers (Nixon and Haldeman), 1968; 1973 (Box 20, Folder 162)
  - Copies of Congress and Senate Papers, 1942; 1972 (Box 20, Folder 163)
    Lend Lease Operations and Watergate Investigation
- Trips, 1969-1976; 6
  This series is dedicated to Riland's trips with Nelson Rockefeller and Richard Nixon. Folders contain official schedules, pamphlets, and mentions of many other of Riland's visits. More information regarding these trips can be found in the Diaries series.
  - Nixon Europe Trip Volume I, 1969 February 22-March 2 (Box 20, Folder 164-165)
  - Nixon Europe Trip Volume II, 1969 February 22-March 2 (Box 21, Folder 166-167)
  - Presidential Mission to the Dominican Republic, 1969 July (Box 21, Folder 168)
  - China Trip and Chinese Medicine (with Richard Nixon), 1972-1973 (Box 21, Folder 169)
  - China Trip Part 1, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 170)
    With information on acupuncture.
  - China Trip Part 2, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 171)
  - China Trip Part 3, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 172)
    Intelligence report and Riland's "Medicine in China" paper.
  - China Trip Part 4, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 173)
  - China Trip Memorabilia, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 174)
  - Russia Trip, 1972 (Box 30, Folder 254)
  - Visit of Richard Nixon, President of the United States of America, to the People's Republic of China: Detailed Schedule, 1972 February (Box 22, Folder 175)
  - Iran, Kish Island - Richard Nixon, President of the United States, 1972 May (Box 22, Folder 176)
  - Tunisia, France, Iran, Malaysia, Singapore, Australia, and New Zealand - Nelson Rockefeller, Vice President of the United States, 1976 March 19-April 4 (Box 22, Folder 177)
  - Latin America: General Information, undated (Box 22, Folder 178)
  - Documents Accrued from Trips Abroad, undated (Box 22, Folder 179)
    Contains NATO pamphlets
  - Momentos from Trips Abroad with Nixon and Nelson Rockefeller, undated (Box 22, Folder 180-181)
  - Miscellaneous Mementos, 1972-1975 (Box 23, Folder 182)
- Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1947-1979; 7
  This series contains records pertaining to Nelson Rockefeller and includes information on Rockefeller Brothers Fund projects as well as Congressional hearings over the entrance of the new Ford administration in 1975. Also included is Nelson's Quality of Life Report on Latin America, schedules of his campaign trips within the state of New York in 1962, to the Midwest in 1959, and across the nation in 1964 and to Europe in 1963. Also included are memos exchanged between Riland and Nelson Rockefeller, a copy of his Vice Presidential speech and assorted funeral materials.
  - Correspondence, 1947-1960 (Box 23, Folder 183)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 23, Folder 184)
  - Correspondence - New York State Politics, 1958-1964 (Box 23, Folder 185)
  - Correspondence - New York State Governor's Office, 1959-1961 (Box 23, Folder 186)
  - Correspondence - Osteopathy, 1961-1966 (Box 23, Folder 187)
  - Funeral Program and Condolence Letters, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 188)
  - Health Reports, 1967-1975 (Box 23, Folder 189)
  - Speeches, 1969; 1976 (Box 23, Folder 190)
    "The Future of Freedom" and "Remarks at the National Conference of UPI Editors and Publishers"
  - 1964 Campaign Trips and Itineraries, 1964-1971 (Box 24, Folder 191)
  - Brussels Trip, 1963 (Box 24, Folder 192)
  - Europe Trip, 1969-1972 (Box 24, Folder 193)
  - Israel Trip, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 194)
  - "The Conservative Apparatus and the 1968 Republican Nomination" (Box 24, Folder 195)
  - Subpanel II Report - Special Studies Project, Rockefeller Brothers Fund [Nelson Rockefeller's notes], 1957 December 4 (Box 24, Folder 196)
    Autographed by Nelson Rockefeller with inscription "To Ken from an old friends and admirer - Nelson Rockefeller"
  - House Hearing on Vice Presidential Nomination, 1974; undated (Box 24, Folder 197)
  - Annual Message to the New York State Legislature, 1972 January 18 (Box 24, Folder 198)
  - Rockefeller Brothers Fund, 1960-1965 (Box 24, Folder 199)
  - New York State Trip Schedules, 1962 Fall (Box 25, Folder 200)
  - "Quality of Life in the Americas: Report of a U.S. Presidential Mission for the Western Hemisphere", 1969 (Box 25, Folder 201-202)
  - U.S. News and World Report Interview, 1975 October 13 (Box 25, Folder 203)
  - Memos, 1969-1974 (Box 25, Folder 204)
  - Mementos from Trips Abroad, 1976 (Box 25, Folder 205)
- Clippings, 1945-1974; 8
  This series contains news clippings about many of Riland's famous patients, Nixon and Watergate, Tom Seaver and Henry Kissinger.
  - Patients, 1974 (Box 26, Folder 206)
  - Tom Seaver, Riland Banquet, School of Osteopathy, Nixon, 1968-1973 (Box 26, Folder 207)
  - Kremlin Drugging, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 208)
  - Herbert W. Kalmbach, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 209)
  - Nixon, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 210)
  - Nelson Rockefeller, Nixon, Medical, 1964-1969 (Box 26, Folder 211)
  - Nixon and Watergate, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 212)
  - Riland and Nixon, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 213)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945-1972 (Box 26, Folder 214-215)
- Scrapbook and Photographs, 9
  This series contains various photographs that were originally housed in a bound album. Additionally, clippings, mementos, and articles found in a scrapbook have been removed from their original housing and filed accordingly.
  - Slides, undated (Box 30, Folder 249)
  - Scrapbook - China, undated (Box 30, Folder 250)
  - Photo Album, undated (Box 30, Folder 251)
- Closed Material (Box 31)
  Restricted - confidential material. Closed until June 27, 2042 as per the deed of gift. Originally, the material was reviewed by archivist Harold Oakhill. Pages from the diaries containing information to be closed were photocopied and restricted. The final restricted copy was placed in the open diary papers, and the originals have been placed in a sealed, half size letter box at the end of the collection. During processing in 2021, the folder was unsealed and reviewed again by Amy Berish. The papers will continue to remain closed until 2042 as per the deed of gift.